all right welcome thank you everyone for
joining it
is the first early session for cohort 7
in this second phase of
activity so anybody who uh wants to sort
of just check in
with uh that I guess we could have done
before starting recording but just want
to check in where are we at in this
cohort as we head into the second half
of this textbook in people's view or
what would they like to do for this
phase of activity for the kind of second
half for this cohort and then we will
turn to chapter
six um maybe
ali uh and then anyone else who wants to
raise your hand or just go for
it uh okay so uh chapter six actually
marks the um uh beginning of the second
part of the
textbook uh as we probably already uh
know the book organized into two
different uh parts so part one is mainly
theoretical and part one part two uh
basically deals with more practical
applications of active
inference uh
so as as we saw in the first part of the
uh textbook um the theoretical
Foundation of active inference is
actually work in progress so uh it's not
something uh that that has been
uh uh completed uh in order to applied
uh as a kind of uh comprehensive uh
modeling tool but at the same time uh
the second part of the uh textbook
provides very promising road maps uh
to um towards how we can apply even
these uh
tentative foundational work um in order
to build uh some real
World models of the intelligent agents
or cognitive agents uh so I think that's
important to keep that in mind because
uh in many textbook groups uh I've seen
people uh somehow uh rais this issue as
to well it's not as comprehensive uh as
we thought as as a modeling tool so uh
since the public a of this book U
obviously active influence research has
progressed a lot uh but
even the uh the theoretical foundations
provided in the uh first part of the
book uh I believe provides enough
material to um at least build some
uh Toy
models uh that can capture some of the
real world element
of a real um a real world agents or at
least cognitive
agents thank you Ali great anyone else
want
to share with their ad as in this uh as
we head into this part of the
textbook yes so uh I think I would like
to do that um I missed the first half of
this um group uh so I'm I'm asking a
question which belongs to chapter two I
think or chapter three I don't know um
and so my apologies for that and I don't
want to
hijack the discussion here uh and I've
put my question also in the in the chat
but basically comes down
to um having tood the role of PR in um
active inference as having a dual role
which is one kind of the intuitive role
for me at least being vely familiar with
bence inference is you know encoding
prior beliefs and also um having a kind
of indicator role of
encoding uh preferences and I think this
comes out of uh discussion of
um ocular motor Behavior as well as
other things and I was just wondering if
you have discussed this at all and uh if
I've yeah if a brief comment on this
would be great but if you say well you
should have you know attended the
previous sessions and I'm fully happy
with that as well and then we'll just
tag along for the right for
now yes um there's
a slide in this the point raised in this
paper um that points
to Prior being used as a um preference
to drive pragmatic behavior in lie of
for example what a reward function does
for reinforcement learning because when
things are framed in terms of likelihood
directly
rather than projecting onto a explicit
rewarder
utility uh function only just working
with a base joint
distribution
um then the prior can be seen as
preference
constraint so it's like the preference
for blood sugar has a different
connotation and and um function and
everything than one's felt psychological
preference for something or revealed or
stated
preference but
um at
least um from a modeling perspective
it's more similar than
not okay so I'll I'll have a look at uh
those reses thanks
so okay
Jerry yeah I think as as we're going
into at least my area of interest and my
questions are you know based in my field
of work which is marketing and
Communications and just how to apply
this to you know um consumer Behavior
you know to to actually build some
models that use these principles and
these
Frameworks um so that we can have
replicable studies um within this type
of a
field great well chapter six is a great
place for that because uh uh it is a
recipe set of
questions with more in common than uh uh
with just
general uh statistical experiment
planning and systems engineering and
systems modeling
broadly uh with a connection in specific
ways to get to the kind of generative
models that are described in basically
chapter 4
and there's a lot of uh distance
between where the this uh current text
from 2022 will get you and the code
running in your
hands uh but that's a ground that is
also rapidly being more traversible
too and uh and so building out examples
so that they're specific
uh just you know there's there's a big
gap there but that is it represents um
in in a sense just how many degrees of
freedom there really are in
probabilistic
modeling yep that makes sense and so
yeah I'm excited to to dig into it it
definitely seems like it's an area that
uh is ready to be
explored cool so I wanted to share this
uh one little experiment this is from
earlier today it's linked in the chapter
page so I took the text of chapter 6
just plain text put it into this PL tax
repo used cursor
IDE to restructure it and obsidian link
it so now here it is um with probably
some light uh you know
edits
but has these links out to all these
other
topics also this
repo you can just put a new file and say
write a PDP type model for this because
it has this whole knowledge scaffold
that that we can also all contribute to
so I think a as the uh
years and the application Niche
changes chap uh the textbook and chapter
six like Ali said it will always be
interesting to consider how it's like oh
yeah just these matrices alone are kind
of like a good representation of
modeling this or
that
uh all the way on through however that
gets friction and a lot of degrees of
freedom in application when there are a
few standardized open-source methods and
it's unclear how to necessarily
Implement just an equation into an
actual program they like um or there can
be multiple it just like oh why is there
not just one KL Divergence function or
like why don't we just have a
variational free energy function there's
sometime it sometimes it gets very uh
data form
specific computational environment
specific mat lab Julia all these like
things that come up in the
application so I think that's one of the
biggest changes between
2022 um as uh some will remember in
terms of like we'll think okay before RX
and
fur pmdp mat
lab now better augmented coding and
knowledge engineering tools code
generation
tools
um
helping with some of that especially if
we uh can collaborate I believe and have
some people working with these code and
program synthesis approaches to the
structure learning and kind of uh
sketching out more the Tex tree of the
spaces of generating
different aspects of specific
uh generative modeling uh
passages and then also people who are
just like wanting to model or do inquiry
into a specific like yeah do there have
more squirrel crossing the bike path on
Tuesday those kinds of uh test
experiments so um
but this is the application part it's
almost like the textbook coming back to
domain uh even though that kind of
happens in chapter 5 to an extent so I
hope that in this phase
for we can uh
possibly return to some of the code
questions that have come up over the
years like having code
examples for
um you know chapter 7 in chapter
uh some of which we already have more uh
Advanced things open source so it' be a
subsetting not like a making but also
these things just from being specified
can be made very quickly to a first
pass so if we want to to um develop the
code and also the questions
around going through
application that would be really useful
maybe maybe I could share my um project
that I'm working on and then when it
comes up relevant
uh I'm Andre from Lithuania Andre kowas
does anyone want to start with a
specific question about chapter 6 or the
book first and
then then let's do projects but not
um begin with it thank you address
what should we really do in synchronous
and
asynchronous for the textbook the 2022
textbook is a great art artifact
understand and learn from I mean any
section or any question can be
useful um though really I am
I
just nice nice
drawing hey Daniel um yeah at least
you're just asking questions there like
the the one up there about affordances
is always of interest to me as well as
you know maybe how like variational
script might come into play if that's
applicable as
well yeah what what about
it um I
mean I think at least from from my
perspective um there was some stuff I'd
read Around creating fields of
affordances which I felt kind of tied
from a consumerism perspective
to how Brands go out to market for
instance um and so maybe the question is
more around like not just affordance
generally but that idea of like how do
organisms in this model or how would we
test
um how agents select between the field
of importances through those either I
don't know if that's through policy
selection there that's my assumption but
um you know still newer to thinking
through this from a like actual
application
perspective does anyone want to say
something to
that
okay the first question in the for four
question recipe here is what's this
system are we modeling and then if we
were thinking about an
individual uh Mouse in the tmas like
what's going to come up in chapter 7 in
discrete time it's like okay are we're
going to model it with four locations
starting left right and
down uh or are we going to model its
footsteps so if you model footsteps then
there's going to be the the explicit
you're going to have some data structure
that represents the footsteps location
like data about it Andor
simulated distributions about it but if
you're going to just say well not it's
not a footstep modeling project it's
just a a location for state that which
is what's going to happen in chapter
7 so um just from this sort of Applied
angle which system are Remodeling and
that's kind of reflect that the earlier
comment about this having more in common
especially early in this process with
systems modeling and systems
engineering it's just like okay the
organism is a very complex Locus person
at a game machine or something but but
um like the complexity of how hormones
interact with uh you know sound and all
this or something or microbiome those
are all part of the real environment SL
situation SL system but you might be
able to get away with a 3X3
Matrix for just three uh states of
vigilance low medium
high because those kinds of modeling
um
uh that's just oh
all models uh map
territory all those kinds of topics that
that come back and but it's like right
it's a it's a model of this it's an
inferred parameter it's a risk factor
for x or it's just a mutual information
estimate on percentile on this in our
model so it that it that's why this
whole process where chapter 6 actually
gets one isn't necessarily some um G
paradigm shift on their modeling view
per
se that you couldn't necessarily also
have from doing a regular gen
generalized linear
modeling which can also be very
sophisticated and deal with higher
order um variance and causal relations
it's kind of
like generalized probabilistic
modeling combined with cognitive syst
systems approaches to systems
engineering okay yeah that makes sense
in the footstep model when you brought
that up I think that kind of resonates
for me because we'll talk a lot about
customer Journeys and one thing I've
been thinking about is just you know
using the T the term consumerism like I
don't know that we think about it the
right way in my industry and so I've
been looking to biology a little bit for
a better analogy and so like predatory
behavior for instance like the process
of identifying and detecting and
consuming and then processing something
I think is an interesting corollary to
what we probably ought to be doing when
we talk about you know communication and
purchase and stuff like that so that's
that's interesting and helpful um and
maybe that's something I can dig a
little bit more into is that idea of
more modeling footsteps versus locations
which I think we tend to try to model
the end the location when we ought to be
modeling like the steps towards
that yeah so the the hierarchical models
at least in principle which is kind of
where the second half of the Tex goes is
is um where you have slower inference
models you know and then a faster ones
and then uh it's just a project or
situation
specific empirical question about how
much compute and what kinds of specific
models you're going to
make um so so this let's continue on as
people if if they want to bring in their
um you know how they're seeing that or
some other section of the of six or we
can go to the questions but just yeah
this first question is like is like okay
we're
modeling everything about the Biometrics
of the person or just this those are
such different questions but those are
questions that are also just dealt with
everyday in animal behavior cognitive
modeling okay but here's where we start
getting more into some of the technical
analytical
details of the structure of these
models that relate to making some more
committed model
decisions not not just agreeing that
okay we're we're just interested in
um this question about this system of
interest um so that that the next three
questions are the three practical
challenges these can be specified um
like they go into more detail in chapter
6 and there's there's more sort of links
into guides and experiences people can
share and and just try and explore uh
through but basically it's like keeping
in mind that the textbook here uses
generative model to describe the
agent type uh unit and the generative
process to be the
environment um whereas also generative
model can be used just to be the
total um model
specification basically the three um
areas of questions
are how do you want to deal with
time um model it
discreetly like or in continuous time uh
these are questions common to other time
series modeling
approaches um even if you choose
continuous time you know how will time
discretization
on if Will that matter for your data or
for your
compute um what is going to be the
structure um in hierarchy
[Music]
um laterality like just message passing
is it just like are you
modeling one abstract decision maker
making one sequential response to one
put data just as an intuition pump or is
it doing like this data to here and
wanting this output so that's just sort
of the um getting to specifics about the
model
structure which can again just be either
specified
uh for from Simplicity like just be
often the models are just a
single uh PDP partially observable
Markov decision
process and that that um can't
necessarily be directly picked up to
work on a large data set or something
like that but for certain purposes it
might be all the research question needs
at that stage but um again that's kind
of a separating like okay we know the
systems have hierarchical depth so what
parts of multiscale complexity are
modeled so that's just a common modeling
question and then what is the
time how do these different agent or
generative model specifications
themselves deal with
time so just some it's uh things that
come up but these are more in common
with uh at this point like statistical
modeling
causal inference machine
learning AI also these kinds of
questions would come
up here is where it starts to get more
into um some of the
uh
basian
uh degrees of freedom of modeling like
are you going to model a parameter as
just fixed like a a spike in the
probability space like not learnable you
know how learnable how
variable and how what are you going to
do with how you specify and update and
fix how learnable and how variable are
you just going to say from this previous
study we know the variance of this trait
to be 10 so we just fixed the variance
at 10 or we learned it but um you know
if everything is learnable there's just
the Looms a greater problem just like in
uh uh reward learning when when they get
into meta learning and all this how
learning how fast to learn to learn and
all the sort of things
is um I mean the larger the state space
and
learnability of the
the of the kind of Target Model you make
an optimization challenge by making it
so open-ended by dealing with large data
by dealing with complex
data maybe there are some
structures of probabilistic models that
have excellent computational performance
on certain
situations but that's a hope and a
preference and uh is not the case that
that that uh you know any
given uh probabilistic model would be
performant in any given way on any given
data
set however there might be some that are
really really
effective or or the huge families that
are adequate for certain
uh uh processes but but but we're we're
getting into statistical
modeling so that's kind of
from coming coming to this from an
empirical biology behavioral modeling
perspective and seeing how mostly here
we're just talking about
how some this could be said and probably
many parts are said across
different cognitive and
behavioral modeling works
but it's working within a
specific probabilistic modeling
framework that has connections to the
free energy
principle um sort of path of least
action
approach coming from The High Road
chapter six sort of brings us back to
the low road and building up the
specific
systems that um also have the extension
into the
implementation Methods at least uh some
as we sort of explored a little earlier
but it
um getting
[Music]
from the
uh questions about the specific
system to the probability distributions
in families and mod model that that meet
up in the Middle with the sort of high
road
approach is basically where chapter 6 is
but there's no it's like these questions
are all common to statistical
modeling efforts and there's other
things I'm sure people here too could
add of just the sort of um her istics
and pitfalls and important questions for
interpretation of complex systems
modeling another sort of I mean
another
uh practical question is
like um where what is the what there's
different ways to do projects and and
research and everything but does someone
want to just imagine a model where
there's a
10 time Horizon and a five of this and
it takes in this data it's like is it
just being
sketched as part of a
[Music]
thinking process
or is this
wanting to be used for doing statistical
modeling because the sometimes there's
moves that are
possible in just sort of drawing
connections on paper that might be very
uh there's that might be like hard
within current
implementation
approaches so in the examples of of the
code we kind of are building out
specific
um motifs that are
useful but the the way that people are
thinking about
systems um is often very
nuanced and so it's I I I mean I I hope
people can in the
second uh phase here like let let uh
figure out how to make it useful also
just discuss what do we really want to
do with these meetings with recorded and
unrecorded part
because we we we can figure out
other
um other ways to have our shared
attention and work I don't
want to uh feel
like returning to this and just
re-recording going back to the same if
that's not the most useful format
this
to kind of break the to kind of break
the silence here I'm not PR sure because
like what um what what do you usually do
like what is your usual um mode of like
navigating uh the second half of the
book like the Practical part of the book
um like for instance someone uh like I
think Andreas was about
to sorry I was about to talk about his
project I think hearing about uh like
the projects that people are working on
like how they're implement all this
stuff that would definitely
be sorry that would definitely be
interesting for me um also for my own
project like I don't have anything
specific yet but for the coming meetings
I think it would definitely be
interesting to um to discuss the
specifics of that but I'm I'm not sure
what other things you you would yourself
suggest J Daniel or like what has worked
for uh previous previous meetings but
that would be interesting for
me thanks you yes okay we can return
that's a good suggestion for Andreas um
in terms of what has been useful people
can look through the previous chapter
6 uh
meetings but I I think what would be
very useful is
to
uh connect specific questions and ideas
that people have to segments of the text
if only as an exercise in anchoring and
and Scaffolding off of the
2022 text um maybe just as a jumping off
point in moving to other
resources
um
then
uh working through these questions and
figuring out what other questions they
asked along the way
to get to they wanted to go with a
probabilistic model that that they
um could share uh back and uh connect to
implementations uh tables that that we
have to the textbook
examples so sort
of it to if we want to make models in
given domains let's make them over these
coming months according to this recipe
Andor making our own but uh at least
taking this
recipe uh seriously as or even as a
subset of things that we do
Andreas how about just go for your
question let's see where it goes yeah uh
so um um to introduce myself I'm Andrew
kowas from Lithuania I learned about
active inference a year ago from Daniel
and I've had many conversations with him
I've read the first six chapters and so
I'm attending at this time U every week
uh and so what I'm interested in
modeling um I'll say generally and then
specifically generally I have this uh
I've been documenting my own human
expence uh as a conceptual language and
so
I'm uh one way that comes out is like I
I feel like I live my life through three
Minds there's an answering mind a
questioning mind an investigating mind
so like if I raise my hand there's me
that knows what to do and I just tell
myself to raise it and I don't have to
think very much about how it's being
raised or where it's being raised so and
similarly like there's all kinds of
answers that come into my head so that's
the unconscious um these answers and
then there I have another part of mind
that's this chattering language uh words
or or concepts but I think of them as
questions so like when I think of like
the word horse it's really a placeholder
for what the answering mind might tell
me as a horse and so I have this
conceptual language and then I have um
this full-fledged Consciousness which I
call the investigating mind willful
cognizant
deliberate which basically tries to um
line up the other two because
get the same information in two
different forms so the unconscious knows
all these things the unconscious doesn't
know them and so can have the
information that two and then like with
conom okay
I apologize can you hear me
yeah continue I apologize on so I was
talking about this investigatory mind
which aligns the other two what we know
what we don't know and then like with
Daniel conman's Thinking Fast thinking
slow it's able to decide hey here I
should just think fast and and where
here is here I should think rationally
you know so go with my Intuition or
should go rationally I'm trying to model
that so specifically how could I model
especially and I think there's a
language for each of those like so
there's a language of how things come to
matter for the unconscious there's a
language of how meaning arises like
verbalization for the conscious and
there's a language for
how
okay not sure if his connection
staple um
yeah Danel to the last part he was
talking about I I think I have a
question maybe tack on to that about
like when he's talking about system one
system too yeah does that in some way
tie to like how we would try to model
novelty versus habit um in terms of like
you that's something I've been thinking
about as well like a lot of behavior
that we notice in my field is is habit
but we're trying to catch attention I
think through novelty
um to train something new in there yeah
like um
to that um and also a little bit about
between habit and deliberation which
Andre I hope we'll start to get at some
of these points that that we can
continue to um work on and develop
in here in chapter 5 so not to go back
but um chapter 5 reviews the some of the
key model motifs from the Maman
neuroanatomy cognitive modeling
literature um studying people's brains H
that being where friston and others have
focused a lot of their work um so as
sort of like well this is sort of what
it looks like to study a complex system
uh like the brain on this so here are
two different um extrema modes of how
policy priors like how apt one is to do
something
before receiving the next
observation and uh policy
inference uh getting to a policy
posterior which action is sampled from
so it's like the differencing of what
was apt to happen before to what was apt
to happen after for action and these are
the distributions that are calculated
during policy uh inference planning as
inference actually implementing planning
agents you will have one um or the other
or a modulated blend of these as as it
turns out to be for the brain for policy
inference on the left is a habit passed
through mode which is like cached action
preferences which can be conditionally
set on the right is the expected free
energy
calculation which is uh discussed more
in the first half of the book and we can
look at
implementations in PDP or in uh other
implementations in this phase of
activity but this is where specific
counterfactual policies of a given
temporal Horizon are rolled out like
policy research and evaluated in terms
of expected free energy or free energy
the expected future um so explicit
policy roll out reweighted energy based
learning consideration of epistemic plus
pragmatic value of policies
um know large
computational
blowup just like any other tree based uh
policy search so that's where um
secondary
teristics like um bounded TR searches
and policy switching and things like
that uh come into play for for making
these models large but often again it's
only a simple one with four policies
being considered or something or 16
policies being
considered but but this has that sort of
multi
combinatoric um computational complexity
if explicit probabilistic or to the
extent explicit probabilistic rollouts
are
used um and then on the left is like
basically just a pass
through so broadly that connects to the
thinking fast and slow and I think I
think some papers
have made some um points but it just
sort of
a it's a functional uh stratification in
cognitive
systems that and then that is being here
modeled by one switching parameter not
map and the territory all that it's like
could there be two switching parameters
but that's the
whole experimental
[Music]
biology question
and I would jump in to say like with
marketing um there's very much the
opportunity like you can sell to
somebody's reflexes or you can sell to
somebody's rationality and if you're a
buyer you know you kind of want to have
both satisfied you want to feel good um
instinctively and you want to feel good
in terms of you know your rational
judgment uh and so I apologize for my
bad connection but I wanted to say um
what I want to model specifically I
think would be um uh this language of
how things come to have meaning which is
relevant for the rational mind so
because the mind that just works
instinctively it just doesn't need to
know all these things but once you
introduce this second rational mind it
needs to think both you know has to kind
of be aware of both ways and kind of do
do its best with this other
mind so I thought well mathematics is
something where things don't really
matter but the meaning arises all the
time and I thought I would look in
particular to a very narrow field which
would be triangle geometry and it turns
out in that field there's an
encyclopedia of triangle centers and
basically like everything interesting
about triangles is basically like a
center of a circle so you can build that
center of a triangle so to speak in
60,000 different ways but to to focus on
the very simplest way um if you put a
circle in a triangle it doesn't matter
what the shape of the triangle is but um
if you expand it to the maximum size
there will be three points that it
intersects that it touches on the
triangle and the property will be
because the radius of the circle is
fixed that from the center of the circle
it will be equally positioned you know
distance-wise to each of those three
touching points so that's called the in
circle so one way is to try to imagine
these two minds as communicating that
problem so the unconscious mind kind of
imagine it it places the circle in the
Triangle you know you're giving a random
triangle and you're kind of like blind
so the unconscious mind places a circle
in the triangle and it's allowed to
expand the tri the circle until it
touches something and it has to stop and
mathematically it'll only touch one side
basically like probabilistically it's
impossible to touch more than one side
at a time and then the conscious mind
will say okay I want you to move but
let's say it can't it can give an
instruction to to move but uh the motion
will be random in some random Direction
so or I guess it has to move it has to
move away from the it has it only has
one direction it has if it doesn't want
it has to move away from the line so it
just moves away from the line at a
certain speed let's say that's based on
the rad proportional to the radius and
then it will the conscious mind tells it
how far to move like how many radi to
move or more like percentage of radi and
then it can expand again it knows how to
expand the unconscious mind and it'll
bump into something else maybe the same
side maybe another side and so through
this iterative process at a certain
point it will have less and less room to
move it'll never know what side it's
bumping into because it doesn't have
that information but it'll just know
that it's starting to bump in very often
on you know which would presume that
it's being closed in and so then the
idea is that once you get within
whatever accuracy you want because it
never touches all three sides at once it
only touches one side at a time um
realistically but um when you get within
1% or whatever you want then you say
okay I'm happy I'll stop and so then you
can ask for example well what can you
deduce about the shape of the triangle
based on the interactions that you had
blind like this you can also have like a
learning process you know then you can
maybe compare that with the original
triangle uh you can um maybe also have a
um a learning process where the
conscious part that decides um how far
to go like how how far to move this um
it can um different policies can yield
different results so it can maybe try to
learn that so I don't know if that was
like a my initial attempt to try to come
up with a way of thinking about this
language and seeing like how active
inference could kind of help to apply
it yeah at least I think that's
interesting what you were saying and it
there's some stuff I was reading by
Michael Levan around like an axis of
persu
with different nested levels of
intelligence that's kind of interesting
to me that I think touches on what
you're you're saying about different you
know I guess lower levels of um the
system learning something and sending a
signal out globally when there's some
sort of an error um but I've been
thinking about that those levels of
persuasion because I think it speaks to
from a communication perspective the way
that we communicate we do it through
unconscious associations we do it more
rationally we do it emotively from a
cultural perspective um but it like you
know I think when it's most effective
it's across all of those levels or that
axis of persuasion that he's kind of
talking
about so is there such a thing as one of
these models that's so simple it could
be coded from a blank sheet of paper in
I guess five minutes
yes that's what the textbook level
focuses on the textbook version is just
five
matrices with it in chapter 7 that's
what this is what you build up
to it's just starting from um Dynamic
perception models partially observable
models observations coming in this could
be a sing binary variable this could be
a three-state variable this could be
continuous V like that's the work of
modeling but then you have a hidden or
latent State temperature in the room
temperature on the
thermometer mapping Matrix initial prior
to kick the chain off transition
Matrix then that's that's equivalent to
a Colman filter like modeling
then you add in some element of policy
selection is it just a binary uh with
two fixed outcomes or do you want to
model this or
that uh conditionality or
learning or or or uh
affordance State St space changing but
you know those are sort of those are
those are structures of models families
of models that you may on your on your
Intuition or or uh fun or whatever seek
to just work within a given model family
just because or not
realize um that you're with within a
given constraint um but it's just what
is it is it just being analytically just
here's like the space of all possible
policies of the organism and I'm about
to make a philosophical point or we
chose to just model the blood sugar not
engaging with other
biomarkers but this is these are the
matrices and the variables that you get
to a b c
d well I'd sort of like to see this
implemented in code uh is that available
yeah great question that's um again
that's what
chapter
6 gets to and I'll just
link I I know it's in the textbook group
um somewhere
hold this is a table of of
implementations if people want to add
and curate more it would be awesome
there's always
uh a lot we can add with these repos
um and if you again these are for people
who want to contribute open
source
resources Andor review them and annotate
them with um like what features they
have like which ones have planning which
ones use this or that uh which ones have
this C I just want like a a really
really simple one you can figure out
what it's doing by
inspection
yeah isn't doesn't appendix C mention
like the T thing that you were talking
about the t- maze is there is there code
for that um there is mat lab code for
that it's a uh in appendix C but we
haven't in a prior textbook group ported
it
but if people would like
to uh work on
that in in the times between
um meetings and uh get it working or
just share what they where they got to
that could be
awesome but making PDP
models and using expected free energy
and variational free
energy
um in the implementations and in this
subsidi um
repo in the cognitive
repo there are there are it's just pdps
with vfe and
EF also I want this is the slide from
the um the the three
PS a distinct rule for the distribution
P this is the same underlying
prior
distribution so if we were modeling like
we're move we're interested in the
movement data of thermophilic bacteria
so we're modeling the distribution of
their location with respect to some
fixed wall so we're going to have some
distribution for their
location it is in the first um frame the
probability of they're existing at that
location at that measured time it's a
it's a latent distribution smooth
analytically um approximable Etc
variational distribution implementable
with software tools for their location
it is also from the co cognitive
behavioral bacterial side as their
preference like our um expected
pragmatic
homeostatic firstness and tendency to um
of certain variables to return to a TR
States and it's the
Fitness in that it's the uh
ecological sampling
availability constituting differential
persistence phenotypically or
genotypically
but that just just that's one it's like
we're doing a Pon distribution from the
wall
any closing uh comments
if if people want to think about what
will make this early time slot in its
alternating you know next week at this
earlier time slot we will go to chapter
2 so if people are um want to just stay
at the same time continuing in this way
we've done it or
just do people have certain amounts of
time they want to set aside or certain
Milestones they want to reach then uh I
I mean I want it to be useful we can
make generative guides and
material
absurdly with people's feedback and help
if they want to make certain kinds of
models so it be it would be awesome to
work on that um but if people have some
other
uh preference for for what would be
good given that we all are here uh for
this time let's figure out so just like
email uh or or at the next meeting add a
note or we'll discuss it oh I just like
to say I think uh some more like coding
Workshop type elements would be good
yeah I I I totally
agree I'll be trying to code what I'm
doing so and I'm interested to talk with
others about you know how they code and
yeah it's like the low road is like the
show me the code Road high road is like
some is
analytical
um symbolic and analytical and axiomatic
uh then sort of qualitative
philosophical stances are included in
that sort of
combination and
uh I think we can we can have some cool
code models please just surface
whichever uh
desada you
see
and let's uh do it so I wanted to thank
uh for the time I apologize for my
connection and just to say like what I
learned was that like what am I trying
to predict I'm predicting where I think
the center of the triangle is and so
when I move the circle from The Edge I
have to make a prediction how far to
move it and that prediction could be
wrong you know and I get feedback from
the from the from the perimeter of the
circle so it's a conversation between
the predictions for the center of the
circle and then the feedback that you
get from the boundary of the circle
that's getting closer to I think
so and I guess for active inference you
really need to understand like
prediction eror like what is the
prediction what's the source of the
error just random point about this
circle triangle thing wouldn't you want
to after it hits the wall wouldn't you
want to grow it in a particular
direction rather than move it in a
particular
direction well I want to have that
dialogue so
um so um the the two steps are you can
move you can grow so the unconscious
mind only knows how to execute this it
doesn't and it knows when it hits
something but it doesn't know anything
really so this blind conscious mind has
to has to have this uh communication
that's what I want to model might it be
better to have grow from the center and
grow in a particular
direction when well the point is that
you don't know where the center is
you're trying to find the center you're
randomly inserted wait I thought you
knew the center of the circle just not
the triangle oh the center of the circle
you know right so and you can only
expand you can grow larger but you can
also grow a circle in a single Direction
rather than from the center of the
circle and and I think that would be a
faster implementation of what you're
yeah I'm not trying to do it faster I'm
trying to do slower so stupider like
what's the stupidest implementation
that's what I'm trying to
do most stupid in revealing thanks
though okay thank you bye